

in linkedin.com/in/ravindersaluja

□ ravinder.saluja@yahoo.com

github.com/ravindersaluja

(+91) 9870609759

Summary ____

Analyst at Tech Mahindra Business Services with background in Big Data and Visual Analytics from SP Jain School of Global Management. Experienced with creating Machine Learning applications for the telecommunication service industry and working with text as well as speech data. Comfortable working with several frameworks including *Pandas, Numpy, Scikit Learn, Keras, TensorFlow and Selenium.* Passionate about programming, open-source technologies, deep learning algorithms, and continuous self-learning.

Experience _____

Tech Mahindra Business Services

Mumbai, India

ANALYST May 2019 – Present

- Implementing Machine Learning models and using them for various ongoing projects.
- End-to-end project management, communicating with the stakeholders, understanding the business requirements and delivering projects accordingly.
- Taking suggestions from stakeholders for improving and making the models better.
- Automating various manual processes with the help of Python.
- Making decks and dashboards for better visualization of the data, thus making derivation of insights easier.
- Leading a team, for scraping data from the web and building a dashboard for improving the advisor efficiency.

MANAGEMENT TRAINEE Jan 2019 – Apr 2019

- Worked on building classification models Naïve Bayes for predicting the contact reason of the customer which helped the Advisor in resolving the customer's queries efficiently thus making the customer experience better.
- Built dashboards using D3.js for showcasing the key contact center KPIs in an interactive manner.

Edwise International LLP Mumbai, India

FACULTY May 2017 – Jun 2018

- Taught quantitative analysis to students appearing for international standardized tests like GRE, GMAT and SAT in group settings.
- Trained newly recruited faculty members for different branches.

Education _____

S.P. Jain School of Global Management

Mumbai, India

Professional Certificate Program in Big Data and Visual Analytics.

Class of 2018

Watumull Institute of Electronics Engineering and Computer Technology, Mumbai University

Mumbai, India

B.E. Electronics and Telecommunication.

Class of 2016

Projects

Current Project: Change Of Tariff (Upgrades), Python (pandas, sklearn) | Analyst, Tech Mahindra Business Services

- The objective is to identify customers who are likely to upgrade their tariff by creating a predictive model, trained on the customer demographics, usage, history of interactions and other derived attributes and also providing the probability rate and likelihood of the customer opting for upgrade.
- The customers thus identified will be converted through various campaigns which will help with the uplift in margin for the organization.

Speech Analytics, Python (ffmpeg, SpeechRecognition) | Analyst, Tech Mahindra Business Services

- The aim of this project was to transcribe the speech of the advisor and the customer into text and then further do the speaker diarization for the same.
- This helped the Quality Monitoring Team in making the audit process faster and thus requiring a smaller number of FTE's for the given task.

SOCIAL MEDIA ANALYTICS, Python (pyquery, requests, BeautifulSoup, textblob) | Analyst, Tech Mahindra Business Services

• Developed scrapers for social media websites like Twitter and Trustpilot for scraping the tweets and reviews about the client and the competitors and deployed this on the AWS EC2 Instance so that the data could be fetched at a scheduled time and the dashboard hosted on the internal server can be updated accordingly.

NEXT BEST ACTION, Python (pandas, nltk, sklearn - Naïve Bayes) | Analyst, Tech Mahindra Business Services

- The objective was to prepare a classification model that would categorise the type of text data received on real time basis and give the advisor suggestions as to what next steps should be taken.
- Approach: Clean the text data using various methods of the NLTK library as well as create custom methods for correcting spelling mistakes, preparing word list dictionary and n-grams, and finally creating a Document Term Matrix from the corpus with the help of CountVectorizer which was passed to the Naïve Bayes classification model.

UK MOBILE MARKET WATCHDOG, Python (selenium, AWS EC2 Instance) | Analyst, Tech Mahindra Business Services

Developed scrapers for various telecommunication websites in the UK with the help of selenium and extracted fields related to
price plans which helped with the tariff comparison and deployed these scrapers on AWS EC2 Instance so that the data could
be fetched at a scheduled time and the dashboard hosted on the internal server can be updated accordingly.

CUSTOMER PHONE BILL - PDF SCRAPING, Python (PyPDF2, re, os, zipfile) | Management Trainee, Tech Mahindra Business Services

• The objective was to scrape the phone billing information of customers from unstructured pdf files stored in zip archives, transform it into a structured form and load the information thus scraped to the SQL Server database.

ATTRITION PROJECT ETL, Python (sqlalchemy, pyodbc, win32com) | Management Trainee, Tech Mahindra Business Services

• The aim of this project was to build an entire pipeline for automating the process of building a data mart for the Employee Attrition Project right from extracting the spreadsheets from Microsoft Outlook to transforming it into the required format and finally loading it to the SQL Server database.

Tools/Frameworks ______

Data Preprocessing: Pandas, Numpy.

Machine/Deep Learning Algorithms: SK Learn, Keras, TensorFlow.

Natural Language Processing: NLTK, Textblob, Gensim.

Development: Selenium, Requests, BeautifulSoup, MS SQL, Git.

Data Visualization: Pandas-profiling, Tableau, D3.js, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Bokeh, Plotly. **Cloud Services:** AWS EC2 Instance, Google Colab, IBM Watson Studio, Kaggle Kernel.

Community __

Organisation/Groups

- Member at Google Developers Group.
- Member at PyData Mumbai.
- Member at AIDL (Artificial Intelligence & Deep Learning)

Additional Certification

IBM AI Engineering Specialization

Languages _____

English, Hindi.

Credential ID: 9FYWT34G9QJT